all right well i you ready to go yep i'm
ready
hey everyone let's get this started um
we usually like to intro and thank our
speakers but you all know who will is so
if you can all just give will wright a
big
round of applause and thank you for
showing up so let's go
[Music]
um
yeah can you all hear me okay am i
amplified
oh good the voice of god um first of all
cell phones off
um no photography and fill out the
registration forms that i'll remind you
about later
um and they made me say all that stuff
so uh
let's see i wanna start introducing
chris right here who's going to help me
with my presentation a little bit today
she's been working with me as a
co-designer for about five years
and i'd like to start by also
apologizing first of all the translators
because i tend to go
really fast and because i always just
want to cram so much into an hour but uh
if you can't keep up feel free to just
make up stuff and
it might be better than what i'm saying
who knows um i also want to apologize
for the title of this talk in the
description
which i know is kind of hopelessly vague
um what usually happens every year is
gdc they call me up and they say we want
you to talk and
i say okay and then a week later to say
what you're talking about and so then i
think about it for a while and oh
i get a rough idea what i'm going to
talk about let me give them some kind of
generic title in that area
that's what usually happens but this
year was different this year when they
asked me what i was going to talk about
i just flat out lied um
but uh so i'm never going to talk about
the future of content um
i'm really more in fact going to talk
about a possible future of content you
know it seems like
the theme that i'm coming away from this
conference with so far
is that the next generation titles are
going to be incredibly expensive we're
going to have to build mountains of
content
and it's going to drive most of the
smaller players on the market
and i'd like to offer potentially an
alternate vision of that you know i
think that there is a way to deal with
that
more creatively
so maybe more accurate title for this
talk would be what i learned about
content from the sims
now you've probably heard me talk about
this a bit so we're going to do this a
little fast
um first of all content is very
expensive uh
this is a list of the content we had in
the sims 2. and
um compared to the sims 1 it's you know
just a mountain of work
to make that stuff um going back across
the games i've worked on
looking at the team scaling up i showed
you the slide last year if you saw my
talk
if you look at the content side of that
it's growing disproportionately to the
team size you know so it's scaling up
non-linearly
um so it's trending way up and i think
that's kind of what we're hearing at
this conference today
um you know one problem with that is
that you know for us to do twice as much
content
cost us about twice as much effort but
yet the value to the player
really isn't twice as much you know this
is just basic util
utility theory if you're on a desert
island and i give you an apple it's
worth a lot you know to keep you from
starving
once you have 100 apples you know the
101st apple is not worth that much
um so i think you know we're fighting
kind of a losing battle here
um on the other hand we've seen that
players love making content um
time and time again every time we've
given the players opportunity to make
content they've just gone crazy with it
um on our website for the sims 2 we've
already got something like
17 000 characters people have uploaded
10 000 houses etc
um now obviously not all this content is
great but even if only 5 or 10 percent
of this is good in fact
the percentages are getting better i
mean in terms of what's really good
content players are making
it still represents a huge amount of
content that the players are willing to
build for us
this is one of our larger websites
phantom websites they just had a
celebration for their hundred thousand
object that people uploaded on there
another thing we found from the samsung
is that metres can be extremely useful
when we're doing games you know we can
learn so much from players by studying
uh
their play patterns what they buy what
they do the verbs they choose
um that we can use for various purposes
we see the players hate boundaries you
know we're seeing a trend toward more
open-ended games you know especially
unnatural boundaries where they just hit
kind of an invisible wall in the game
um one of the issues there is that as we
try to scale up the size of the
possibility space for the player
the development effort again is kind of
a non-linear thing to build an emergent
game it takes a lot of iteration
um we're currently trying to kind of
push that curve down a bit right now
by building more emerging gameplay and
we need to also start fighting it on
getting super content development um
i think there's kind of this inbuilt
assumption that the amount of value that
a player gets from content
is probably a function of the quantity
and the quality of it
um we can take it you know title like
pikmin and you know it doesn't have that
much content but it's very nice looking
and probably the area described
there roughly equals the player value um
we could take another game like katamari
damacy
you know which has a lot of content but
a much lower quality you know quality
and it feels like about the same amount
of value so from that i think we can
kind of infer
this gradient um that we're kind of
currently when we think about the amount
of content that we do in a game
you know we're following somewhere in
this gradient in terms of how much value
we're providing to the player
i think this is missing a very important
dimension though um
i think you know the ownership that we
can give players over content
uh feels like a very meaningful new
dimension that you know by pulling that
out just a little bit
we you know add tremendous amount of
area to that player value
you know so maybe we don't need as much
content and i didn't need it as high
quality
if the player made it they're really
into it
um this is my guy from grand theft auto
his name's mo he doesn't really do the
missions he's kind of a slacker
he rides his bike all day and learns new
little bike tricks on his bike um
but i love it when he goes into the cut
scenes you know this guy's wearing his
you know
cute underwear and his barbie watch and
they take him very seriously in the game
somehow
but you know i after i play the game i
go tell my my daughter and my wife's
stories about what moe did today
and you know i find that you know
ownership
over you know the experience translates
for me in a much more meaningful story i
never go tell somebody
you know the story about the cut scene i
just saw in a game but i'm always
telling people about the weird crazy
thing i did that was very you know
unique to me very you know uh
i really owned the experience and i was
driving the story i was playing the
story
um and so i contend that player stories
will always be more powerful
than scripted stories that we try to
tell the players um
and i'll kind of revisit that a little
bit later
so we've got these trends kind of going
from you know more linear gameplay to
more open-ended
um steeply rising content costs that
we're fighting
you know the value of player generated
content um metrics that we can capture
from the players
um so perhaps a more accurate title for
this talk today is going to be
what i learned about content from the
sims and why it's driven me to
procedural methods
now i started way back on the apple ii
uh
remember this a great machine
um and it was six times faster than a
teletype
this is actually from one of their ads
back then we programmed everything you
know just you know right down to the
metal
in you know machine code we actually had
memory maps we knew where everything was
in memory which is kind of cool
and actually you know what was in memory
about half of it was code and about half
of it was data
um you know the memory was in such short
supply that we had to you know
use as little data as absolutely
possible um today that ratio is probably
more like 101.
um then this happened uh cd-rom came out
and at that point you know compared to
the amount of memory we were dealing
with and these little tiny floppy disk
drives with 140k
on them and stuff um this thing was you
know a super tanker
we could not conceive of this much data
um you know where in the world are we
gonna get all the data to fill this
sucker up
um and so the trend started moving
toward
you know finding ways to create lots of
data to pile into our games you know and
one of the games that kind of really
exemplified this for me
well actually uh before i talk about
that i mean this basically was
kind of like the meteor that came in and
sounded the death knell for the
algorithm
you know in some sense uh this is when
data you know
started to really ascend and reign
supreme you know in our industry
one of the games that really exemplified
this for me was miss you know which was
a very elaborate
slideshow um it was actually done in
hypercard i mean robin and rand i
thought it was a brilliant game i loved
missed i loved all their games and the
fact that they managed to do this in
hypercars as a slideshow but yet still
making you immersed in this world was
absolutely remarkable to me
um and one thing that always occurred to
me though playing missed was that
you know there's this really cool
immersive experience but they had a
great time building this world
and i kept thinking that over and over
boy you know this is kind of fun to be
in
but i wish i could have made this world
that was the fun part
now you know while the rest of the
industry was kind of you know
going off into the data driven you know
let's fill up a cd-rom with lots and
lots of content
there was actually kind of another tribe
on the other side of the world that kind
of
kept the old ways
they basically worshipped the algorithm
kind of kept practicing
their black arts they adopted kind of
modern dress and technology
but uh and that tribe seems roughly
centered on
northern europe scandinavia ground zero
around helsinki
and we call it the demo scene
and these guys are basically crazy
they'll take you know these little tiny
things 64k
and through algorithm generate huge
amounts of
animation and visual stuff and music and
sound
and just amazing things algorithmically
procedurally
and just to give you kind of some sense
for how insane that is
if we take that 64k and we square it
square it again square it again
and again and again and again and again
okay that's a cd-rom over there okay
so you know why in the world were they
doing this what was the point
um they actually evolved out of the
cracking community they would crack
games and then uh
kind of sign their name put a little
screen at the front saying who cracked
the game because it was kind of a you
know
a little competition they had and then
eventually they got more animated more
elaborate visual
um eventually got very cool you know and
if you haven't seen any of these i
really encourage you
and then they have these rituals they
get together and practice their black
arts together
and um anyway i just kind of found this
just incredibly inspiring over the last
few years
so um probably a more accurate title of
this talk
is what i learned about content from the
sims why it's driven me to procedural
methods
and what i now plan to do with them okay
so the first thing i did was recruited
an elite team
of developers skilled in the old ways
um no slight tangent here sorry
my daughter was five you know many years
ago and i decided i was going to get a
really nice telescope and a really nice
microscope you know and
i could find a telescope everywhere you
know all these different science shops
nature company places like that
and i went to go look for a really good
microscope and i couldn't find one
anywhere and it really surprised me
because
you know i've used a really nice like
stereoscope in school and i really loved
what you could do with these things
and um this is just kind of you know
well's personal information you might
find valuable
uh really you know if i had to pick one
of the two i'd pick the microscope you
know especially with a kid these things
are so cool to play with
um and i'll tell you what you get
because now we have ebay and on ebay you
can get these things very easily whereas
before it was like a real treasure hunt
to find one
you basically definitely want one with
stereo and lighting overhead lighting
and they come in two types they come in
low power and high power and you want
the low power
as counterintuitive as that sounds i
mean and just you'll put your hand under
this thing and you'll spend an hour just
obsessing over your hand
and it's like a religious experience but
anyway back to our story
um so
so we recruited this elite team of
developers um
then i put them in a state-of-the-art
hidden development facility
um and started working on this thing a
little while back
um now what i'm going to show you today
uh actually is a little bit of the
results of what we've been working on um
normally i don't really do demos but
actually i really wanted to
demo this first to this community just
because i feel so much affinity for this
community rather than like an e3
marketing type thing
um so what i'm going to show you first
of all it's very unfinished
it's kind of held together with you know
bailing wire and duct tape um
a long way to go but i think you know i
can show you enough of it to where
you'll get some sense
of why i'm excited by procedural methods
and i think it is relevant to kind of
you know what people have been seeing at
the conference here today um
we're calling it spore and that's we're
going to move over to this screen here
okay we start
here and we're in the land of the very
small
i'm actually controlling this little guy
around here um this is basically
cellular scale we have like some fluid
dynamics
um this basically is a very analog
fluid version of pac-man so basically
i'm
trying to eat these little dots uh these
little bad things chase me
um certain ones like these guys can kill
me too
ah that's bad um i have certain
abilities in this world
but uh this world is pretty much
entirely procedural
it's usually generated now the abilities
i get from this guy
after i eat enough little of these food
pellets i get to lay an egg that little
yellow thing is my egg here
um i now actually get to go to the next
generation of the guy i can click on the
egg
and go into an editor if we can bring
the lights down just a little bit if
that's possible
um so here's a little editor i have very
simple
parts that i can kind of build for this
guy i have mouthpieces that influence
what i can eat i can either eat filter
food or i have a probiscus i can poke
into things
um i have different movement methods
flagella cilia little jet
um and weapons like name assists spikes
whatever so i'm gonna take a little
spike here
put it on the front of the guy um and
then go back into the game
and i've actually modified this guy's
abilities now so whereas those brown
things used to kill him
now he can go in and attack them
and i still can't go after the brown
guys but um now i have a new food source
now i could change
my movement and get faster i could get
stronger um so basically the character
that i'm controlling
here is something that i've designed in
the editor um
now over time as i'm playing this game
uh the camera kind of pulls out the
depth of field
you know kind of res is down this guy
grows as it gets more complex
um i'm going to skip ahead just a little
bit in his life cycle what you're
actually doing is you're playing through
several generations here
um and at every generation you get the
ability to go in and kind of modify it
so this is a bit later in the game we've
actually gone now from a 2d
to a 3d environment and now rather than
living in a little you know drop of
water
we're living kind of under the ocean now
this entire world you see here is
procedurally generated
um especially the guy which i've created
as a player when i say procedural i also
kind of include player
creating things being very malleable in
a procedural way so for instance um the
player creates this character but the
animations
behaviors textures are all generated
procedurally
now this guy has a life cycle very much
like the little cell guy did
he also competes with other creatures in
the environment
another thing to realize here that's
kind of different is that all the
creatures in this environment
are coming from other players look
around here a little bit
let's run over those guys
now when i say coming from other players
what i mean is that they are
asynchronously
being sent to your computer to fill out
your world we're actually building a
balanced ecosystem depending on what
your world needs
we deliver other players content to pull
out that world around you
now like the cell game you know this guy
when he reproduces he lays an egg
click on the egg and now we go into the
editor
now this is the editor for this guy um
you can see he's kind of made out of
parts
um the editor here is roughly a mixture
of kind of mr potato head
erector set in clay i can grab the parts
and manipulate them
um i could even pull them off um
and worf them so i'll pull that off i
can grab the
spine here manipulate it you see there's
an underlying skeleton here which gives
me some clue is kind of internal
structure of the guy
and like clay i can roll the mouse wheel
and actually sculpt him smoothly
to give him his outer form
now these things are built out of
functional parts that actually have
meaning to the guy
um in terms of how he's going to behave
and live in this world
these parts also have are mutable
so let's pull off this tail here
the part categories um come in
functional divisions
so these are graspers um a lot of the
parts also
have some functional value besides their
primary one so that's a grasper as well
as having a little bit of a weapon
ability
but it's primarily grasper this is a
three-jointed leg
make a little bit smaller
um these are feet so basically i've
taken my little swimming guy i can also
scale the parts as i put them on
um so i've taken my little swimmy guy
and basically pulled his fins off which
is going to mean he's not going to swim
too well now
um i'll put let's see
another leg there
so this guy is going to be a tripod
guy um so the player can build like
really unusual characters in here
the system will analyze what they built
and then kind of bring it to life all
procedurally
so um we'll bring this guy back into the
game
and because he lost his fins he doesn't
really swim too well now
so i'm gonna actually have him kind of
leave the ocean here
now the walking you see here is all
procedurally generated based upon an
analysis
of the skeleton that you created um in
fact every verb in the game
is as well and once again you know the
world you're seeing here is procedurally
generated
other creatures coming from other
players um
like the other levels this guy has to
kind of survive this guy's a carnivore
so i'm going to have him
eat and have him come in and attack this
guy
now the way he's fighting is based upon
where i put
his weapon which is on his tail
so you can see you know i'm not close
enough it won't hit
so i basically have to chase luckily i'm
faster than this guy oh there we go
get off my head yeah okay
so we killed this little guy
now we can actually start eating him
now one of the cool things about
procedural verbs is that they can be
cleanly mixed
um for instance i can tell this guy take
a bite out of this guy
and then tell him to walk at the same
time and use that to actually invent a
new verb
which is to drag
one of the real wins though is that
whatever i've created in this game is
going to behave differently i mean you
know it's just going to be fundamentally
different behavior than anything that
you might create in the game
uh which is a huge win
and oh okay he's a bad guy
this is where you say run away
now your game actually builds kind of a
balanced uh ecosystem so you're not
always the top of the food chain here
um on the other hand this guy's kind of
fast
and you know maybe he has something on
his stealth and maybe i can outrun these
stupid little hoppy guys
and he'll go eat one of those guys
instead
let's see
i think i might be safe
yeah okay so one of the next things you
do
basically you live out lifespan of one
of these creatures um
and then you basically mate which earns
you access to the editor and you earn
currency at this level the game so i can
do a mating call
and try to find somebody to mate with
okay we'll see how that goes
i'll kind of approach carefully
yeah that sounds good okay
okay and then we get to the procedural
[Applause]
mating
okay enough of that silliness
then we lay an egg and that gives us
access to the editor where we get to
create the next generation of creature
um now i want to give you a little bit
of a sense for
how open-ended this really is i'm going
to load a few creatures that we've
created in the editor
um just give you a sense for how
creative the player can be with this
um this guy
i call him buttface but notice he has a
rather non-standard leg configuration
but um
but still it moves very smoothly um very
realistic very lifelike
um you know one little kind of subtle
trick we're playing with here is that uh
you know people have never seen buttface
before so they don't know how he's
supposed to move
as opposed to humans
here's another one now all the ones i'm
showing you here are actually running
the exact same script
um this guy's got kind of a large head i
call him tweety bird
it's kind of like an suv or this is the
ford explorer like whoa
[Applause]
[Music]
i suspect he would have low fitness in
the world
let's see this guy called hang dog he's
very cool
he kind of walks cool too
but again you know basically the same
code running on all these things that
you know analyze what the player's done
and then kind of animates them brings
them life there's also a whole
procedural texturing step that we don't
have integrated into this
like i can't show you right now but the
ones in the world you saw that were
procedurally textured
this guy i call dilemma
so the function of these guys is a you
know a combination of the parts that you
choose for them
and also kind of the topological um
structure that you set up so this guy
just happens to have a very fast walking
gate
and it's a property of kind of the way
the procedural animation deals with that
skeleton
so a lot of the kind of performance of
these guys is going to be emergent you
know
from the system and of course i insisted
to the team that we had to do a care
bear
so here's our care bear
i'm gonna make him a really mean
carnivore you know
so anyway that's our little evolution
game so far
so one of the things we want to do with
these with this editor here is to make
it a toy it's in line with the gameplay
when people were playing the sims they
had to go out to a separate you know
place download a tool
do something with it then upload it to a
website we really i want to burn the
tools into the gameplay
and then make the portability of the
content transparent to the player
i don't have to go to a website and say
i want some cool you know creatures from
my planet
they should come to me automatically it
should be able to analyze the way i'm
playing and bring them to me
automatically
um i've seen a lot of evolution games
and most of them really did not you know
i didn't feel like i owned the creatures
that were created because it was a very
simple like you know pick from the set
of parts
or these three slots you know a head
body tail to kind of get that
um as a kid you know i grew up you know
just loving dinosaurs you know and
kind of the generation i'm from that was
like what kids did and you know
even then it was very much a paper rock
scissors thing you know by learning the
different types and the names of the
dinosaurs you know it's kind of cool
that i knew what an ankle source was my
mother didn't
you know and that gave me a certain
ownership of those um you know today
it's more likely
something like pokemon you know these
things you know have very elaborate rule
sets and structures that kids learn
and then you know they feel some sense
of mastery over these things
um now just imagine if they could create
them you know from scratch
and that's kind of what we're trying to
do um neopets as well you know one thing
that actually
is amazing is that as you start giving
these things properties you start
naturally mapping narrative into them
um going back to care bears for a second
uh they were i don't know how many of
you know but they were originally just
greeting cards
they were invented by american greetings
for greeting cards if you're feeling bad
you give this
care bear card or if you're feeling you
know this way you give that care bear
card
um they had very specific properties and
specific friends and little superpowers
and stuff
they're actually web apps you know right
now i filled out one of the little
psychology apps
that tells you which care bear you are
turns out i'm sunshine bear on the
bottom corner there
um and just when you think you've got
all the care bears memorized they go and
invent care bear cousins
which they're not bears at all they're
all these weird things
except for that little yellow guy at the
bottom looks like a bear with a tail and
they don't even live in the same place
they live in forested feelings the care
bears live in care a lot
um so the care bears are up here in
caroline and apparently forced to
feelings is below carolina because when
they fall off the cloud they land there
and earth is even below that because
when they have to go on missions they go
all the way down to earth which would
put them somewhere in like low earth
orbit
um and they collectively refer to this
as the kingdom of caring
um and they never specifically say it
but they kind of imply that earth is the
kingdom of who gives a
because that's that's where they always
have to go on their missions
but
but i digress
our lead artist ocean quickly coined
this phrase artist in a box you know
we're looking at all the things that an
artist would typically have to do to
create content in a game and figure out
you know how can we possibly
automate all these things and then give
you know a very simple set of controls
to the player to where they feel this
incredible creative leverage
um the stylistic dimension that we would
like the players to kind of traverse
is somewhere between like pixar and
giger
i don't think we're going to get quite
that far but i think it's the right
dimension so we want players to be able
to do like these
kind of dr seuss worlds or these very
realistic kind of scary worlds
in the game um in essence what's
happening is we have the player here
manipulating a very simple little system
um and that's their leverage on the
thing
the computer takes that very simple
little system that they've built
um and then generates out the much more
elaborate data sets the mesh
the textures um this is actually some of
the procedural texturing that we're
doing where the player has
control over which scripts run and they
can be combined to get a lot of really
interesting results and
they actually analyze the topology of
the mesh so you get it knows where the
back is and the belly and all the stuff
also the animations which you saw and
then eventually the behavior of these
things
which can be player driven as i was
driving my little character around the
world
or they can be npc driven you know when
i pull in other players characters and
they're living in my world
um you know the computer is now
controlling those things
eventually you get this you know very
elaborate cool looking realistic thing
in the world and what this represents
actually is a creative amplification
of the player's efforts the computer is
really an amplifier here a creative
amplifier on what the player's done
and if we look at how small we can
actually compress these representations
of you know the stuff that i was doing
in the creature editor could probably be
compressed down to about 1k
bytes in memory with animations and
textures and all that stuff
it's more like five megabytes and so
that's something like a five thousand to
one compression
now that buys us a lot of things first
of all it gives the player the
tremendous leverage creatively
it means that we can store a huge number
of these things in a very small database
so even if you don't have a network
connection we can give you a little
database
you know on the cd with your game that
contains tens of thousands of these
things already if you're not connected
to the net
it also gives us very low friction for
moving these things they're very cheap
to move around
from player to player peer-to-peer or
server host
and also the same things that we do to
give the player leverage are almost
exact same things you would want to do
to build a generative system
um the computer can be playing with
those knobs just as well as the player
um very much like you know when
somebody's making a face or character in
the sims
they're doing sliders it's going through
some process creating the finished
content
and this is kind of basically mapping to
the idea of a genotype going through
embryology
to an initial phenotype and that
compression is vital for this whole
thing
and those levers again as i said can be
pushed either by the player or by some
generative system
so the pollination that's happening here
is as you build a creature
um it actually gets sent up to our
server this is one model
actually a lot of models could work here
could be appeared up here as well um
where we're sorting the best content and
we're categorizing it they're also
categorized
by things like their life cycle and how
they behave in the world how big they
are what they eat
um so we can do parametric mapping to
the content
um in the meantime your world kind of
requests we need people to fill out the
world that i'm going to be competing
with
and they get pulled in to build a little
ecosystem around you um
so that's basically kind of the
pollination idea here where the world is
being built around you continuously as
you play
um let me go back over here
to the editor now there's one more
palette at the bottom here
which is the brain palette now this is
what you're really trying to do here
is you're trying to save away a little
bit of funds as you're playing the game
and slowly invest them in the brain this
is kind of like your say your college
savings account
you know a lot of times you're buying
stuff oh i'm getting beat up i'm going
to buy you better weapons or i'm going
to hide or run faster
but if you can save a little bit extra
you start investing in the brain and
work your way up kind of this ladder
now once you get the highest level brain
your creatures actually become sentient
and you move to the next phase
now at this level the game actually
mutates from kind of a first person
eater
to an rts now we're controlling a whole
little herd of these guys
um now one thing that uh
i talked about landmarks last time in my
talk last year and i'm going to show you
just a few of the landmarks for me in
the design
one of the landmarks is i've always been
fascinated with the idea of monkeys with
guns
and i don't know why you know but just
what happens when you give monkeys guns
you know it's just
there's something cool about that so at
this level rather than you know
the creature is now set you've evolved
the creature um at this level i can buy
them tools
um and i in this case i'm shopping for
tools and i'll talk about the shopping a
little bit later in this case i'll buy
them a spear rack
they get excited we're seeing kind of
more elaborate procedural verbs at this
point you know they'll kind of have a
response
decide what they want to do with it
now before they get into trouble i'm
going to buy them a campfire here um
these guys are still a bit excitable uh
but i'm actually dealing with the social
dynamics at this point um
depending on how they play them they can
become very emotional or very logical at
this level of the game
uh let me buy them a drum
i bought them at drama now these guys
decided to start playing the drum
um and
this is actually procedural dance you
know based upon
my creature
[Applause]
so at this level of the game you're
playing it kind of like populist or
something i'm buying them tools it's
influencing what they can do i can
control groups of them now i'll send
them out on like hunting parties
and i'm in fact competing with other
tribes um
at this level the latter that i'm
climbing is i'm really upgrading their
hut
um and so i'm gonna buy them a better
hut here which will allow me to buy the
better tools
um and also allow my my tribe to grow
and i'm competing with other tribes for
members
uh they have to do with food and stuff
like that um
now they're just basically living in
this little corner of the world i'm
going to skip ahead a bit here
um if as i upgrade the hut here
eventually i
upgrade it uh to the next level which
brings me um
to get the next game which is the city
game
now at this level we're basically
playing a very very simple version of
simcity
um i can you know decide what buildings
to make them i
build roads uh they have needs
um and basically i'm trying to keep them
happy in their little city you know and
again i have
complete creative control over
everything you see here
you know so i am you know the player is
the author of this little world
now like the tribal mode um we have a
shopping thing here now
the shopping is populated actually again
with other players content
um so if i don't feel like building
something you know and i just i see
something really cool that another
players made it'll try to learn the
style
that i'm using and try to populate my
shopping catalog
with things in that style and then i can
pick them
here and then buy it
or you know if i see something i want to
modify or i want to build something from
scratch
i can actually go into the building
editor um which
and we're trying to make the you know
all the editors in the game um
feel very very similar uh this is using
similar kind of morph block stuff
you know basically everything in here
has like a handle and i can kind of play
around with it
shape it you know like these little um
we have categories you know from very
platonic solids
that have certain handles on them
now the building editor is a little bit
closer to legos really
um i can grab an object and i can have
it intersect
or stack um you know try to find the
simplest possible operators
you know the average person can very you
know quickly learn and this becomes a
toy to them you know they really have a
lot of time and we found this a lot in
the sims build mode by the way
the players would go into that mode
there was a little bit of a learning
curve but they had kind of immediate you
know
feedback and they got so much creative
um
reward for doing that that uh i've been
looking at how we fold that experience
more and more of the gameplay okay so we
basically added this little mushroom
thing to our building we'll go back in
the game
there it is over here so they're they're
happy they like it
the primary feedback for me in this game
is kind of the
happiness of my people and they you know
now we're dealing with like large-scale
kind of social interactions between the
characters um
as i mentioned before the tribal game
you know uh this is my city but i'm
actually competing you know with other
cities um if i scroll across the map i
can look for neighbors
so here's another city now this city was
created
in the exact same editor um just using
you know slightly different primitives
um different texturing you know from the
procedural texturing but just as
to give you a sense of the variety of
style that a player can do so our city
was kind of what we call maybe dr seuss
style
um this is more kind of
techno-industrial star wars style
but these kind of demonstrate a little
bit the kind of pixar pixar to gear
dimensions now these guys also will have
a very different culture than my guys
you know depending on how they
we evolved and how i you know dealt with
him or how the
computer dealt with these guys uh during
evolution and tribal
these guys are really kind of more
aggressive a little bit more industrial
um at some point once you upgrade your
city enough um
you get the ability to start building
vehicles
this is how the cities actually interact
as a tribal you're actually sending
people from tribe to tribe and doing
raids
or you know trading having you know you
can have kind of good or bad
relationships with the neighboring
tribes
at the city level we basically have kind
of three ways to
capture or ally with another city
they're basically military economic or
cultural
um depending on kind of the cultural
flavor of my people
um so they don't look very friendly and
they're heading our way
so we can open our vehicle editor which
works very much like the building editor
there's a shopping alternative populated
with you know items that other players
have created
um and i'm just going to buy something
here
like that we have parts categories these
have functional meaning so propellers
you know can help the thing fly
uh certain things enable it to go into
water or go on land but um i'm just
gonna go ahead and go for this goofy
looking thing this is kind of the
more of a nazca looking and there they
go
god knows where they're a little goofy
um
yeah go to that city go go go no not
that way
okay so they're peaceful cowards so it's
hopeless
i don't know in the meantime these guys
are
you know not looking real friendly
so this this is kind of militaristic but
uh there are
more peaceful avenues to kind of
capturing cities
at this point in the game we're actually
kind of entering the uh
what i call the civilization game um
and this is a very simple version of a
game like sieve or risk
as we pull back now for the first time
you can see the entire world other
cities now one little trick you might
notice here
is that as i pull away from a city it
actually gets very exaggerated
um this is both for aesthetic and
functional reasons like
as i pull into the city notice how it
pops to a realistic scale but as i pull
out
it actually becomes an icon um that
indicates actually the level of
micromanagement
um at this level the city is one big
button and it has a very simple menu if
i want to go in and actually go and
still modify the cities
i'm still building paris while they're
attacking it i can still zoom in and
click the individual buildings and bring
them into the editor and stuff
um so basically you know you play this
game the civ you know game
you know and slowly conquer the world
you know city by city kind of my
continent until pretty much
you have owned this entire little world
and built it on the way
so that's that
now
now the next let me just
break that down a little bit now
in this part of the game we're dealing
with a different type of pollination as
i mentioned um we have a buy mode
in a lot of these levels and here we're
taking other players content
trying to map it parametrically to your
play style to populate your buy mode
um then you know you might choose to buy
one or actually build your own when you
buy something though
um we're actually using that as a
positive feedback
on what was in the database so we're
continually resorting the database on
the top end
trying to discover the best feedback
based upon how many players actually
used it
and so there's continual sorting of all
the content that we're accruing in the
master database
uh at this point you can see this game
actually has some similarities to wario
incorporated
um in some sense i wanted this to be an
homage to all of my favorite strategy
games
and i know it's kind of like one of the
rules of thumb in the game is don't mix
genres
and so i've always wanted to break that
rule really badly
so you know we basically have kind of
the tide pool level which feels very
much like pac-man that was kind of what
you know evolution which is like diablo
counter-intuitively and i say like
diablo because it's kind of like you go
into this world
and you you know hack and slay monsters
and if you make it out alive you get to
go back to the village and buy better
armor better sword
and then go out back and fight you know
better monsters and that's kind of the
dynamic that you're going through when
you're going to the editor
living through a generation and then
going back um
the tribal level you know really feels
to me like population you know i wanted
to be kind of an homage to populists
which i loved um simcity
of course i had to uh and then sue
which i always loved you know and i
wanted the top but i wanted it to be a
very
light game experience compared to what
most of these games have turned into
i wanted it to be about 20 percent of
the best of simcity
or 20 of the best of uh civilization
because i as a hardcore gamer just don't
have the time to invest in these games
nowadays i find myself spending a lot
more time playing my game boy
i'd much rather have a lighter
experience that distills all the core
elements out and so
i'm fully expecting about 40 of this
experience to be really aesthetic
that the player spends a lot of time
just kind of building a creative world
and for them
it's part kind of light gameplay but
still very open-ended you know very
interesting strategies
but very understandable simple systems
that anybody can kind of pick up and
play like they can play a gameboy game
um for every level of course we have an
associated editor that becomes kind of
the main thing you're interacting with
you know at that level um and really
you know i did not want to put the
player in the role of you know luke
skywalker
or frodo baggins instead i wanted to put
the player in the role of george lucas
or jr tolkien or dr seuss or whoever you
know i wanted the player to feel
like you know they had built an entire
world you know going through these
different levels
um let me talk just a little bit about
the story uh just to deflect the issue
um because i don't have enough time
today to really go in depth of it
but more recently i've been thinking of
story as really a side effect or a
property
of interesting experiences not a
prerequisite
you know so many games that had no story
where i went in and had a great story
you know i don't even know what the
story of grand theft auto was but my
story was really fun
i had a great time you know and it was
very you know relevant to me i own that
story
um and i know it wasn't you know star
wars or hamlet or anything but
still it was my story um you know i
think we use the stories as a filtering
process
on our experience um they emphasize the
causality
of the situation if you look at a movie
the director has the opportunity to show
you exactly
why this guy got upset and kicked this
and broke his foot you know
and we don't necessarily have that level
of control you know
from our side but the player does the
player is always there having the
experience happening to them
um also stories are very useful for
portability you know communication it's
way for us to take an experience that
we've had some other place some over the
point in time
conveying somebody else and they're also
in some sense compression and
abstraction
where we can get general kind of lessons
that we might apply to other situations
even though the stories don't exactly
match
we can abstract up the story to kind of
a schema learning
um and i mentioned this actually uh
last year a little bit robert louis
stevenson when he did treasure island
the first thing he did was draw a map of
the island
and then his eye just roamed that map
kind of imagining all the things that
could play out
and in some sense the story just kind of
emerged to him
so let me go back over here
so here's our little toy world again um
now i want this to feel like a very
clock-like toy world so you'll notice it
actually is very exaggerated
um but in a kind of a stylistic way i'm
gonna go back to our little city here
see how they're doing
i think we have a crater where that
building used to be
in the vehicle editor there's one more
slot that over time we could eventually
unlock as we're playing through the game
um you know we started with ground
vehicles water air underwater
um and at this point uh i can now buy
what we call the ufo
and i'm just gonna buy a stock one you
know i could have brought this in the
vehicle editor as well
now this basically becomes your swiss
army knife at this point you know this
becomes the representation of all your
kind of tools and abilities in the game
this guy is very fast very mobile you
can go anywhere on the planet
in no time at all uh now there was
another landmark that really um
kind of inspired me at this level uh
just a little short side story here
um there was this show i used to watch
as a kid all the time it was called the
mutual of omaha's wildlife kingdom how
many of you saw that show oh yeah
so hey marlon perkins and this other
dude i forgot his name
but uh they would go around every
episode was them saving some wild
endangered animal
you know or some or studying it or
something but what i loved about the
show was that every week almost the way
that they
chose to solve the problem their
environmental problem almost always
involved a high-powered tranquilizer gun
in a helicopter
and so i watched the whole show just for
the scene at the end where the guys in
the helicopter hanging out trying to get
you know going through the herd you know
having the guy um so that was something
that i really wanted
uh with my ufo here um
and so the ufo really one of the things
it is it's a content creation
uh tool so um i can go around looking
for something
um let's see oh these are the guys that
were beating up us on us
way back now it's time for us to get our
revenge
okay if i can get over to him this is a
little tricky
got him yes so here this is basically a
little abduction beam
um and oh that guy's too fast for me
oh i don't want to tank no way i get
that guy oh
man they're hard to get well i guess one
will do
um so i can use this to go around the
world
sucking up content um and as you might
have guessed i can also
use my ufo to kind of go further out and
further out and further out
and further out and further out
[Applause]
so here's our little local solar system
um
a few comets there's our sun uh we have
hot planets near the sun
uh this is our home planet that we
actually evolved on
um and then we out here we have some
cold planets um we can click on any
planet kind of go over to it
and we can actually take our ufos there
to investigate
um these planets really represent like
little sandboxes for the player
so as we pull up to this moon you notice
geologically it's very different
than where we came from than our home
planet um
it's much further away from the uh sun
now one of the things i want to do with
this thing is i actually want to kind of
bootstrap it
um up to life you know and you know
basically build a whole flourishing you
know
civilization on this and i might do a
very different style too so you can view
these as like different palettes
that i have to work with um so one of
the things i want to do is i'm going to
try to get life
on this planet to live and kind of
bootstrap it up i'm going to come down
to the surface here
really quick um now
i'm going to try dropping that guy i
just picked up
um can anybody tell me why that happened
um if we can bring up the volume a
little bit on this machine
um yeah that's good um
so we had a little problem there uh and
we have no atmosphere
okay so what we really want to do is we
want to um
make this world livable now
at this level another one of my kind of
landmarks was an old thing called kid
picks how many of you played kid picks
um
the uh i wanted this to feel like kid
picks basically what i loved about kid
picks is you had all these cool weird
wacky creative tools
and they were always out of your control
i mean you always did these unexpected
oops i didn't mean to do that type of
thing
and i wanted the terraforming to kind of
feel like that as well um so i'll pick
one of my terraforming tools
and these are things that you earn for
the ufo you're actually increasing your
ufo's ability
over time and there are lots and lots of
tools and different ladders so um
we'll fire a little volcano tool
and so this is actually sculpting the
surface of the planet directly
and pumping atmosphere in there
now over time these will actually start
developing a thicker and thicker
atmosphere on the planet
[Applause]
but in the meantime i can actually start
building colonies here even while i'm
waiting for that
so took a spot zoom in
um when i build a colony now at this
point i get kind of the style that i had
on my homeworld
it has a bubble over it um this by the
way is also what i would get if i were
to build at this point
uh city underwater um so at this point
this level of technology i can start
colonizing
the oceans on my home planet and they
would have bubbles as well
um now this kind of takes a while now
once i terraform the planet i won't know
the need to build bubble cities and i
can actually build very elaborate kind
of colonies
um they're earning me money to help me
upgrade my ufo that's kind of the real
loop going on here
um we have a little cheat here you know
this is at the very high levels of the
game
um you'll eventually be able to afford
the we'll call the genesis device
so this will very rapidly if you notice
the ground texture
you see things are starting to green up
a bit we're getting a little bit of
atmosphere um
as the storm clouds pull back a bit um
so we're actually trying to bootstrap up
the atmosphere and then there's the
biosphere score so you
once you get a little bit of an
atmosphere you start then bringing in
plants probably that you've you know
harvested from your home planet
um and then you can actually start
living there so it's like kind of a
three-way colonization game terraforming
game
but really we want players to be
extremely creative kind of with what
they build here
um so let's pull away from this guy
so now it's kind of green that's a happy
little place we have our guys there
um so everything's good um as i
mentioned the ufo has a lot of different
uh
levels that you know you can advance on
the different tools that you add
one of the more expensive things that
you really have to kind of work in here
for a while
and build some usable colonies and a lot
of money but eventually you earn
the interstellar drive and so we pull
out again
now this is our home planet here um we
call it we call this the stellar zoo in
fact we want to have all
the real things that you would see in
space one thing that's always really
annoyed me about the way astronomy is
presented
is it's presented as two-dimensional if
you look at star maps like that i mean
that's the way astronomy is taught
but it's yet it's this beautifully
three-dimensional thing and you just are
not given the sense of what that's like
um we have these beautiful images from
hubble and we're never given any context
for how big they are
where they live how frequent we see them
in space and i really wanted to
at this level give a player a real sense
of what it feels like to be out in the
galaxy
so we have things like black holes
back here we have planetary nebula
and this is basically an old supernova
shell these very bright stars are
like blue giants that in fact are going
to go supernova fairly soon so i have to
kind of stay away from those so there's
actually a terrain here
to this this is the mysterio nebula back
here where new stars are formed
um but also at this level
we uh have a seti tool i can roll the
mouse over different planets and listen
to them
if i i'm listening for radio chat or i'm
actually trying to discover other
intelligence
oh there we that go
there we go yeah it's in an alien
language but i now know that they're
aliens living there
so um we can go visit that star now
so this is a different system that we're
in um looks like they had a little
accident
or something here um
this is another race now this is the
point at which i am overtly browsing
other players worlds
okay so this entire world was created by
another player and now the computer
you know it's downloaded to my machine i
want to emphasize this is asynchronous
um it's not a you know simultaneous
multiplayer game i downloaded it from
the other player
and the computer takes over control
based upon the personality sliders that
the other players kind of set for it
when they evolved it
um so let's go visit these guys
this is kind of a little hot planet
because it's so close to the sun
you can see it has kind of a very
different geology
very arid very large sun there
looks like we have a big city over here
we'll kind of approach slowly
now when we're doing uh first contact
with the other species um you have to
kind of play this little close
encounters musical game with them to try
and establish a language
um and they may or may not respond well
depending on how you play it
so i'll try that now
[Applause]
okay but luckily we have defensive tools
as well
so this is space invaders
uh my weapons are seeming a little
ineffectual against them uh but as i
mentioned you know all of our
you know tools on the ufo come in many
different flavors um
so
[Applause]
uh
so there you go our friends and there
goes my reputation as a non-violent game
developer
but we made a new ring it was a nice
crafts project
you know um so let's pull out to here
we're gonna leave this place there's
nothing more to see here move away now
um okay so
at this level the space level we
actually want to build a set of meta
games
around you know basically my favorite
genres of science fiction each one of
these is going to be a meta game at this
level
um you know starting with something like
war the world um
kind of an adult supervision peacemaker
day of the year stood still
type scenarios um uplift where i go to
worlds that have just primitive
creatures
i can drop down a monolith bring you
know and basically come back later and
see how they've evolved intelligence
to see those worlds um first contact
uh abduction and cross-breeding of
course you know you will have free
access to the uh
to all you know most of the editors that
point you know so at this point i can go
back into the
creature editor for free and make weird
alien you know hybrids
um and diplomacy uh every race is gonna
have its own kind of personality
um we're actually using the star trek
races as kind of landmarks
making sure that we get you know with
the smallest number of dimensions we can
clearly distinguish between all these
races
so that when i go up and interact you
know and i have like the klingons versus
the borg
or my versions of these things that they
should behave appropriately with
each other you know these when i want to
fight or trade or
just be good friends and share you know
cool ideas whatever um
we want the space game to really feel
very very open-ended and this is where i
think most of the narrative is going to
come into the game
um i want the players to feel like
they're creating these worlds if you
look at some of the old comic book
covers from the 30s and 40s
um that's what i want the players to
feel like they can make these worlds
worlds of this variety
if you look at these covers they mostly
you know they have vehicles buildings
aliens and planets i mean so all the
different things we have editors for are
represented on these covers
um this is some of the concept art we
did for trying to get a sense of how
broad we think players can build worlds
aesthetically
now the pollination at this level is
that we're actually doing overt browsing
you know i'm actually going to another
player's entire planet
when i'm on the planet i can actually
you know abduct their creatures steal
vehicles and they enter my library i can
use their creatures to go back
and populate like an entire zoo planet
if i choose to
so really we have these different levels
of gameplay
and the overall structure of the game
now is that of a t
um that we're going up through evolution
through all these different levels
and then we have these very broad set of
metagames
above it at the space level and this is
actually a little bit opposite than most
games because what we're doing here is
we're putting the more goal oriented
gaming first
as the tutorial for this the eventual
sandbox
um which will then surf down through all
these levels most games you think about
the sandbox is kind of the tutorial
that's when you learn to play the game
and then you go play the real
goal-oriented game
we're using the goal-oriented game to
basically train you to use all the
editors
and to teach you the simulation dynamics
at every level so by the time you get to
the space game
you can kind of fractally surf you know
both horizontally you know from planet
to planet
and vertically you know from like city
to sieve to tribal
so eventually um you know with the
players creating
all these different worlds here you know
a little bit more
now the region we were in was like this
little square here
um you know i think we can actually
create
a whole galaxy here of you know
tens hundreds of thousands of worlds
that the player can visit and interact
with
and kind of make up their own game along
the way um
this was you know you might kind of
notice this was an idea i've had a long
time ago was powers of ten i've always
been a big fan of the eames
um but i never in my mind could figure
out a way to kind of roll this into a
game and actually make it all add up um
more recently i started working on a
seti game um
because i was very fascinated with the
seti and astrobiology programs one thing
i noticed at some point though was that
the
interesting terms of drake's equation
and this is the equation about
you know a galaxy has this many stars
and this percentage of them have planets
and this percentage of them have life
um the terms in that equation map very
neatly to the different powers of scale
and so at some point i rolled the two up
the city game and the powers of tin
thing
this is actually one of the first design
dock which uh
wired about a year ago asked me to do a
page for them they said we're doing an
issue
on life and will you lay out a page for
us and i said sure can i do whatever i
want
and i said yeah and i just sent them
this i didn't tell them what it was
and they published it last year so the
design docs have been out and wired for
a year now
um so it's a very simple player story
here um and we needed a way to kind of
you know
compress this whole idea so that people
can comprehend it is that the player is
going from bacteria
to a galactic god um
and that we're kind of basically trying
to you know replay you know the complete
history and future of life
um which it's hard to come with a really
kind of
catchy marketing line for that if
anybody comes up with one let me know
please
um now the the hub that all of this
revolves around
um and i haven't had much time today to
go into the details but the hub this
really revolves around his compression
as i mentioned um the compression gives
us tremendous leverage for the player
um to make them creative which is a huge
win for the player
um it also the same leverage gives us
generative systems
um which we can use to populate huge
content libraries
um also it makes the content very
portable
that we can use to build an unbounded
world around the player which is again
is a huge win
we did over 200 prototypes of this in
fact i've shown many of the prototypes
for this over the years
i just didn't tell you what they were
but um prototyping has become kind of a
religion for us around this
and one last thing i wanted to say here
uh as we're working on this game
you know a lot of the games i've worked
on i've always had obstacles usually
trying to you know to convince other
people it's a good idea or be sellable
or whatever
um when i look back on this idea you
know the biggest obstacle i truly had
was making myself believe that we could
build the game it was my own imagination
was the biggest bottleneck um once i
truly believed that this game was
buildable
it proved to be actually quite easy to
con i mean to persuade the rest of the
uh
of my staff and the executives and
everything that we could do it
um so i'd encourage all of you if you've
got like some totally weird idea
that is just so far outside the box that
you think you know there's no way that
would work
go back occasionally and revisit those
ideas because you know you just never
know
you know where they might lead to and uh
last thing is i can't talk about this
again until e3 i'm sorry i got special
permission to talk about this today
here um but i can't say a word of it
outside this hall
after this until e3 but that's it thank
you very much
you can keep clapping
[Applause]